Okay בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ק"ג kuf gimmel
103. We continue with the משנה mishnah top of ק"ג. kuf gimmel.
Again we're dealing with the question of who's entitled to get to
divide and get a portion of the meat, but our משנה mishnah
switches from the meat to the skin, to the leather, which must
have been obviously clearly expensive. Having recently costed out how much the
hide of a cow goes for,
but clearly its value goes up once you process it, but it's
clearly something of significant value. So the משנה mishnah says: כל שלא
זכה המזבח בבשרה לא זכו הכהנים בעורה. Kol she-lo zachah ha-mizbeiach bi-vesarah,
lo zachu ha-kohanim be-orah. So it doesn't really immediately address the question
of how the כהנים kohanim divide the leather. The assumption is, and
this is going to be said in the גמרא, Gemara, that it's
divided together with the meat and that if you were not entitled
to the meat because you were טמא tamei or something of that
nature, you're not entitled to the leather. So our משנה mishnah though
moves immediately on to say when might the כהנים kohanim as a
class not be entitled to the leather? And then it's not clear
what you would do with the leather; presumably you would sell it
and the proceeds would go to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So
it says when the altar does not merit the meat—now this would
be an עולה, olah, because normally it would be the כהנים kohanim
who would get a portion in the meat, but in an עולה,
olah, if something happened to invalidate the sacrifice and you're not going
to put the meat on the fire, then the כהנים kohanim do
not merit in the leather. Yeah, would it be anything like if
it becomes טמא tamei or נבלה neveilah or whatever it is and
then... Well we'll see. Okay. But if it became טמא tamei or
נבלה neveilah after it was זכה. zachah. So the key phrase is
the phrase זכה. zachah. So זכה zachah does not mean that it
was put on the fire—did I just say put on the fire?
It means that if it merited being put on the fire, which
means that when was it fit for being put on the fire.
So if you look at the first רש"י: Rashi: כל שלא זכה
המזבח בבשרה כגון שאירע בו פסול קודם זריקה. Kol she-lo zachah ha-mizbeiach
bi-vesarah, kegon she-ira bo pasul kodem zerikah.
Something happened before the blood was thrown. So the easiest example would
be that it was שחט shachted with a
פיגול piggul type of thing. נותר Nosar though, if the blood was
thrown and the meat was left over, the מזבח mizbeiach was זוכה
בבשרה—the zocheh bi-vesarah altar was entitled to the meat even if the
meat hadn't actually been put on the altar. Okay. So the question
isn't was the meat put on the altar, but was the meat
fit for being put on the altar? After the blood was thrown,
that would be the moment that the meat would be able to
be put on. So was the blood thrown and in a proper
way that would have made the meat able to go up on
the altar? Now an interesting question not dealt with here is let's
say that the פסול psul is not a פסול psul that affects
the whole קרבן korban per se, but by chance happens to affect
the entire קרבן. korban. For example, let's say the entire meat becomes
טמא tamei before the blood was thrown. Right. So that's not like
something is inherently wrong with the קרבן korban like it was פיגול,
piggul, that it's not able to go on the altar. Right? You
could have imagined that some of the meat became טמא, tamei, some
did not, right? And in that case what? Would only the skin
attached to the meat that had not become טמא tamei go to
the כהנים? kohanim? Does he need some degree of the meat to
go on? Anyway that's not discussed. So for now let's bracket the
case of טמא tamei which could be more local in theory and
let's talk about a type of a פסול psul that applies to
the whole קרבן. korban. So if there was a פסול psul that
occurred before the blood was thrown, like it was a case of
פיגול piggul or something, then the altar never merited having the meat.
The meat never was allowed to be put on the altar. Since
the meat was never allowed to be put on the altar, which
is again determined at the time the blood was thrown because that's
what
determines after the blood is thrown the meat's able to go on
the altar. So if there's a moment when the blood was thrown
the meat was able to go on the altar, then the כהנים
kohanim merit the leather. Otherwise if at the moment the blood was
thrown something was, it was invalid and therefore there was never that
moment that the meat could have gone on the altar, then the
כהנים kohanim are not entitled. So let's say, so just so I
understand, the blood wasn't thrown but you
שחט shachted it
and then it became a נבלה, neveilah, right?
Well it became a נבלה neveilah at the time of שחיטה. shechitah.
Yeah so then the meat was never fit for going on the
altar. So the meat right, so then that means the כהנים kohanim
won't get it. But then if after that, you did and all
the blood became טמא, tamei, no it's then still before. Okay. So
the whole meat becomes טמא tamei after זריקה. zerikah. Then the כהנים
kohanim get the leather. Then the כהנים kohanim get the leather. So
then you'd somehow burn the meat but strip it, skin it first
for the כהנים? kohanim? Exactly. Yep. And similar to if it all
becomes נותר nosar after the blood was thrown. שנאמר: עולת איש olat
ish, עולה olah שעלתה לאיש. leish So it
says עולת איש, olat ish, עולה olah, that counted for a man,
it has to have counted for somebody. So if at the time
of the blood was thrown it counted for a person. Now again
counting, you could throw the blood and the meat could not be
fit for the altar, like I said all the meat could be
טמא tamei but the קרבן korban won't be
פסול, pasul, right? So then it is funny that the shift here
focuses on was... Is the קרבן korban valid, not whether the meat,
the עולה איש olah ish doesn't exactly tell you that the meat
was fit for the altar. Again, if you imagine that all the
meat is טמא, tamei, the blood could be thrown and in theory
you could be יוצא yotze even though the meat was never fit
for the altar. If you start with that, then you have to
go back to our first משנה, mishnah, שלא לשמו ולבעליו. shelo lishmo
ulebaalov. Well, we're going to get to there in a minute. עולה
שנשחטה שלא לשמה, olah shenishcheta shelo lishmah, exactly the next line. So
since we mentioned it counted for a person, what if it actually
is kosher but it doesn't count for anybody? Okay, אף על פי
שלא עלתה לבעלים עורה לכהנים. af al pi shelo altah livalim orah
lakohanim. Now, the כהנים kohanim still get it. So that seems to
go exactly against the דרשה derashah and saying it's really not about
counting for somebody, it's really about was it kosher or not kosher.
So the דרשה derashah of לאיש is funny. And as I said,
the principle of זכה לאורה zakha leorah also isn't exactly a function
of whether it was kosher. It could be kosher and not זכה
לאורה. zakha leorah. All the meat could become טמא tamei before you
threw the blood. So the exactly doesn't exactly match the דרשה, derashah,
certainly not the idea that it has to count for somebody. The
גמרא gemara should ask that. Well, we'll see, the גמרא gemara will
just explain how we get there. אחד עולת האיש, echad olat haish,
now here it's also going to say don't overread the word איש,
ish, whether it's a man, ואחד עולת האישה, veechad olat haishah, or
a woman's קרבן, korban, עורם לכהנים, oram lakohanim, the כהנים kohanim get
it. Or presumably a קטן? katan? Oh yeah, that too. עורות קדשים
קלים לבעלים. orot kodashim kalim livalim. Now
the if it is שלמים, shlamim, the same way the owners get
the meat, they get the leather. עורות קדשי קדשים לכהנים. orot kodshei
kodashim lakohanim. And if it's not an עולה, olah because the פסוק
pasuk is עור העולה, or haolah, whatever,
I forget the whole פסוק. pasuk. עור העולה אשר יהיה לכהן לו
יהיה, or haolah asher yihiyeh lakohain lo yihiyeh, whatever, לכהן לו יהיה.
lakohain lo yihiyeh. Because כי יקריב את עולת איש, ki yakriv et
olat ish,
if a person brings the עולה olah. of a person, עור העולה
אשר הקריב לכהן לו יהיה, or haolah asher hikriv lakohain lo yihiyeh,
or something like that. I should have looked. What, I know לו
יהיה lo yihiyeh is at the end. You know the whole פסוק
pasuk there? Should have looked it up. What's the whole פסוק? pasuk?
It's ויקרא ז' ח'. Vayikra zayin chet.
Here we go, 7:8. והכהן המקריב את עולת איש, vehakohain hamakriv et
olat ish,
there's the איש, ish, עור העולה אשר הקריב לכהן לו יהיה, or
haolah asher hikriv lakohain lo yihiyeh,
right. Okay, so anyway, there you see that the כהן kohen gets
it. Now, so it only mentions an עולה. olah So עורות קדשים
קלים לבעלים. orot kodashim kalim livalim. So if it's a קדשים קלים,
kodashim kalim, it goes to the owners with the flesh. עורות קדשי
קדשים לכהנים. orot kodshei kodashim lakohanim. And if it's of another, like
a חטאת chatat or אשם, asham, the כהנים kohanim get it. קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, and here it's interesting, a דרשה derashah is in
the משנה. mishnah. ומה אם עולה שלא זכה בבשרה זכה בעורה, umah
im olah shelo zakha bivsarah zakha beorah, an עולה olah, where the
כהנים kohanim
don't get the flesh, they get the skin, the leather. So קדשי
קדשים kodshei kodashim by a חטאת chatat or אשם asham שזכה בבשרה
shezakha bivsarah
that they get actually the meat, אינו דין שיזכה בעורה, eino din
sheyizkeh beorah, קל וחומר kal vachomer they should get the flesh, no
they do. They קדשי עורות קדשי קדשים, kodshei orot kodshei kodashim, no,
קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. Okay, if you get the flesh, you get
the meat, it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Okay, and
the פסוק pasuk is only talking about an עולה, olah but from
an עולה olah it's a קל וחומר kal vachomer to other קדשי
קדשים. kodshei kodashim. אין מזבח יוכיח, ain mizbeiach yokhiach,
and don't come back and say what do you mean? The skin
doesn't always go with the flesh, because in an עולה olah, the
flesh goes on the מזבח mizbeiach and the skin doesn't go on
the מזבח. mizbeiach. So how can you assume that by a קדשי
קדשים kodshei kodashim just because they get the flesh, it means that
they get the skin? No, that's not a good counterproof. אין לו
עור בכל מקום. ain lo or bekhol makom. The skin never goes
to the מזבח. mizbeiach. So there's never like a הוה אמינא, hava
amina, it's not a concept that you would ever burn the skin
on the מזבח. mizbeiach. But when we do know that somebody does
sometimes get the skin, like the כהן, kohen, so we know he's
fundamentally
entitled to the skin. Then one can take a קל וחומר, kal
vachomer, if there's places when he doesn't get the flesh he gets
the skin, certainly when he gets the flesh he should get the
skin. But a חטאת, chatat, I mean I know we're not talking
about this right now, but a חטאת chatat if I the individual
כהן kohen do the חטאת, chatat, do I get the meat, do
I get all? No, it's all divided equally. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan.
Okay, that's the whole point, we don't read that if you, לכהן
לו יהיה, lakohain lo yihiyeh, I guess what it means is anybody
who is entitled to, right, to do the חטאת, chatat, it's equally
divided. When they say burn it all on the מזבח, mizbeiach, they
mean without the skin. Without the skin, you flay it, right. והפשיט
את העולה. vehifshit et haolah. It says you, the verse explicitly says
flay the עולה, olah, cut it up into its pieces and burn
it on the מזבח, mizbeiach, and then here it says and here's
what you do with the skin. So it's quite explicit that you
do not put the skin on the מזבח. mizbeiach. תנו רבנן. tanu
rabanan. עולת איש, olat ish, okay, פרט לעולת ההקדש, prat leolat hahekdesh,
דברי רבי יהודה. divrei rabbi yehuda. Only a man's, not to exclude
a woman, only a person's עולה, olah not a עולה olah that
belonged to the בית המקדש. beis hamikdash. What עולה olah belongs to
the בית המקדש beis hamikdash that's not coming from a private individual?
We'll see. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר פרט לעולת גרים, rabbi yose
brabbi yehuda omer prat leolat gairim, to exclude the עולה olah of
a convert. As the גמרא gemara is going to say, since when
is a גר ger not a person? Okay, so two very, we'll
see what it means, two very cryptic interpretations. But I will say
when the עולה olah isn't going to go to the כהנים, kohanim,
whatever these cases are, okay, or take the case in the משנה
mishnah that the קרבן korban was פסול, pasul, it was like פיגול.
pigul. It means that the בית המקדש beis hamikdash takes possession of
the skin, they sell it and they get the proceeds. That's what
you would do with the skin. Okay now, so what do these
two cryptic statements mean? מאי
פרט לעולת הקדש? mai prat leolat hekdesh? אמר רבי חייא בר יוסף,
amar rabbi chiya bar yosef, so what does it mean an עולה
olah. that belongs to הקדש? hekdesh? אמר רבי חייא בר יוסף, amar
rabbi chiya bar yosef, פרט לעולה הבאה מן המותרות, prat leolah habaah
min hamotarot, that basically what happened is that somebody sanctified an אשם
asham and אשם asham became like whatever, somehow got lost, they brought
another one, this is a- so this is an extra אשם. asham.
So what you do is you wait for it to get a
blemish and you redeem it, and what do you do with the
proceeds? Okay, you bring an עולה. olah Okay, similarly, now if that
happened with a חטאת chatas that you brought another one and then
you found your old חטאת, chatas, you'd have to let it die.
But you can have leftover חטאת chatas money going to an עולה
olah. as well, which is that if you designate, if it didn't
start with an animal, you designated money for a חטאת chatas and
you had let's say leftover and you only had to use some
of the money, or you lost those funds, you bought a חטאת
chatas with other funds and then you found the original funds. Those
original חטאת chatas funds would go to for an עולה. olah And
that עולה olah would be- it would go into a communal בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash עולה olah. fund and would not be your private
עולה. olah? What would be the נפקא מינה nafka mina that it
wouldn't be your private עולה? olah You wouldn't have to bring the
נסכים, nesachim, the wine and the flour that came with it. You
wouldn't do סמיכה smicha on it. You would not be entitled to
do the שחיטה. shechita. It would be an עולה olah. that would
be completely the בית המקדש's Beis HaMikdash עולה. olah, So when it
is not a private עולה, olah when it is an עולה olah
brought by the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, there the כהנים kohanim don't
get the skin, there the skin is kept by the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash and sold and the proceeds go to the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. Or the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash uses it directly if
they needed to. Yeah, whatever, exactly. Okay, so okay, הניחא למאן דאמר
מותרות לנדבת ציבור אזלי. ha nicha leman d'amar motarot l'nidvas tzibur azli.
That's good if you say that when you have those leftover מותרות
motarot moneys from an אשם asham or a חטאת, chatas, they go
for communal
עולות. olahs. אלא למאן דאמר מותרות לנדבת יחיד אזלי, ella leman d'amar
motarot l'nidvas yachid azli, but if you say that that means that
the individual brings it, the same individual whose אשם asham it was
now uses that money to bring a- what do you call it?
Now uses that money to go ahead and bring an עולה olah,
from that money, but it's his personal עולה, olah,
okay. So מאי למימר? mai lemeimar? So then you don't have that
category. כי דאמר רבא. ki d'amar Rava. No, so רבא Rava will
explain you can still say that's being excluded, but not being excluded
really by the emphasis of איש ish versus הקדש hekdesh because it
really is your private עולה, olah, but from the ה, hei, okay,
or העולה. ha-olah. העולה עולה ראשונה. ha-olah olah rishona. We have another
דרשה drasha that says how do you know that nothing comes before
the עולת תמיד olat tamid because it says העולה, ha-olah, which means
that this is the first one. That's a different דרשה. drasha. But
we're going to say a similar דרשה drasha here: עולת- olat it's-
it's or
ה- ha what is the פסוק? pasuk? עולת איש או העולה. olat
ish or ha-olah. So it's not from the דרשה drasha of עולת
איש, olas ish איש ish versus הקדש, hekdesh, it's from the דרשה
drasha of העולה. ha-olah. Only something that was originally sanctified as an
עולה, olah not something that is only an עולה olah. because it's
the money has been diverted to become an עולה. olah, Okay, הכא
נמי hacha nami העולה עולה ראשונה. ha-olah olah rishona. So yes, same
point. Even if this funds go for your private עולה, olah, since
they have been repurposed funds, the הלכה halacha that the כהנים kohanim
get the leather doesn't apply to it. Okay, so that's obviously not
פשט, pshat, פשט pshat was that we're talking about it's not a
private עולה, olah. it's the- it's הקדש's hekdesh עולה. olah, But if
you say there isn't this idea of הקדש's hekdesh עולה, olah, we'll
say fine, it might be a private עולה, olah but it's a
repurposed עולה olah. and therefore the הלכה halacha that the כהנים kohanim
get the leather doesn't apply to it. Right, so what happens with
that? They get- the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash keeps the leather. Okay,
so that's one דרשה drasha that it's excluding a private עולה. olah,
I mean, it's excluding a repurposed עולה, olah. rediverted-
extra funds that went for an עולה. olah. רבי אבא אמר רבי
ינאי Rabbi Abba amar Rabbi Yannai says a different הלכה. halacha. פרט
למתפיס עולה לבדק הבית. prat l'matfis olah l'bedek habayis. No, no, the
case is here I am, I sanctified my cow Bessie here as
an עולה. olah, And then I said, you know, I so much
want to give this to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash that in
addition to sanctifying her as an עולה, olah? I'm also going to
sanctify her on top of that as a gift to the temple
treasury, בדק הבית. bedek habayis. Now of course that's bizarre. How can
I do that? First of all, what's left to give to the
temple treasury? It's all going to go up on the altar. Okay,
so is there- is that a relevant concept and is it even
mine anymore after it's an עולה? olah. Is that a relevant concept
at all? So there's a discussion in the גמרא, Gemara, a different
גמרא, Gemara, that I have to basically redeem it and use that
funds and give that funds to the temple treasury before I can
bring it as an עולה. olah, But is that only rabbinic, biblically
I really did nothing when I sanctified it to the בדק הבית?
bedek habayis? I mean he said to do it twice. Yeah, I
mean Bessie is worth ten thousand- a thousand dollars. So Bessie's going
to go on the altar, and but because I also, after making
her an עולה, olah sanctified her to the בדק הבית, bedek habayis,
I have to redeem that on
a thousand dollars and give a thousand dollars to the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Now is that a just rabbinic, because really
my הקדש hekdesh shouldn't do anything? Or no, somehow it's biblical that
she could both be an עולה olah and belong to the בדק
הבית. bedek habayis. That's a debate. So we're saying that let's- that
somehow because she was sanctified, you know, to the temple treasury, that
means that this is also the temple's עולה olah. and therefore the
כהנים kohanim keep the- the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash keeps the leather.
So now the גמרא Gemara is going to clarify that. Let's take
a look. So it says like this.
לא מיבעיא למאן דאמר קדשי בדק הבית תפסי מדאורייתא. lo mibaya leman
d'amar kodshei bedek habayis tafsei mid'oraisa. If biblically now she really is
owned by the בדק הבית, bedek habayis, so then okay, so then
she's Bessie's עולה. olah, Now the point is you're not going to
מקריב makriv her as the temple's עולה, olah you're going to redeem
her first. But the point is that maybe since at one stage
she was owned by, you know, what do you call it? בדק
הבית, Bedek Habayis, she was owned by the Temple, so even though
not at the moment that actually presumably it's being slaughtered and whatever,
but that's enough to take it out of this category that the
כהנים Kohanim get the leather. אלא אפילו למאן דאמר לא תפסי, Ela
afilu l'mon d'amar lo tafsei, even if you say that biblically really
she doesn't become owned by the Temple Treasury, it's all just some
rabbinic thing, okay, to get, and so nevertheless, הני מילי בשר, hani
mili basar, what I wasn't able to sanctify after I had made
Bessie an עולה olah? was the flesh, because the flesh was heading
to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. But actually, even though that biblically didn't get
sanctified, you know what did get sanctified at the time my Bessie
was moving around here and still mooing yet after she was an
עולה? olah, You know which part of her I still own? The
leather. Okay. So it's interesting, even though the כהנים Kohanim are going
to get the leather, since the leather doesn't go up onto the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, when she is an עולה, olah the leather that is
on her right now, you know, her skin, is not defined as
עולה olah yet. Okay? It's the leather surrounding an עולה olah. that's
going to be given to the כהנים Kohanim once she's an עולה.
olah But the only part of her that's an עולה olah. is
the stuff in the leather, you know, not the skin itself. That's
not an עולה. olah, So therefore, when I sanctify her to בדק
הבית, Bedek Habayis, even if really the whole animal isn't owned by
the Temple Treasury because that's already an עולה, olah the skin is
now owned by the Temple Treasury. So why can't it mean that
I just one minute, הני מילי בשר אבל עור תפיס? hani mili
basar aval or tafis? The עור or would be, and therefore the
כהנים Kohanim do not get the עור, or, the עור or is
going to retain in that type of case. Now the question is,
do I slaughter her without having redeemed her? Can you actually slaughter
her and actually have it that you have בדק הבית Bedek Habayis
leather here and the meat is the is goes on the מזבח?
mizbe'ach? If that would be true, that would, I guess, be pretty
obvious then that it would not go to the כהנים Kohanim because
it was already owned by בדק הבית. Bedek Habayis. But again, it
sounds like since the הלכה halacha is that you're supposed to redeem
it before it gets slaughtered, it sounds like the חידוש chiddush is
further. It sounds like the חידוש chiddush is even after you've redeemed
it and then slaughtered it, since there was a time when that
was owned by the בדק הבית, Bedek Habayis, that is enough to
say that the כהנים Kohanim don't get it. That seems to be
the point. Yes, Michael. Wait, I mean, it seemed like to me
the reason why we said, oh, well, you know, you have to
redeem it and slaughter it and then whatever, is because what was
left? So but if we say from the very beginning that the
כהנים Kohanim never got the עורות, oros, so if I then מקדיש
makdish as an עולה olah and then the בדק הבית, Bedek Habayis,
why can't we just say just one thing? No, just bring one
this as an עולה olah and then give the עולה olah to
בדק הבית. Bedek Habayis. So I don't... That is what we're saying.
No, you're saying we have to redeem it and then you know...
it's like a double pay. Why not say a single pay, meaning
I give it as an עולה olah and then give the עולה
olah to בדק הבית? Bedek Habayis? Yeah, I think because you do
not want to be taking something that belongs to the בדק הבית
Bedek Habayis and slaughtering it and so on. But yes, I understand.
That's the flip side of the point that I was saying, which
is that the הלכה halacha is that you redeem it and nevertheless
it goes to בדק הבית Bedek Habayis even after it's been redeemed.
All right, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, where were we? אבל עור תפיס. aval or tafis. וכן אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, V'chein amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah
bar Avuha, the וכן v'chein is going on the earlier statement, this
case about מטפיס matpis was a little strange. פרט לעולה הבאה מן
המותרות, Prat l'olah habah min hamutaros, where it's the case about when
it's an עולה olah. that has been used by repurposed funds, okay,
which is a communal עולה. olah, That's the כהנים Kohanim don't get
it. אמר ליה רב המנונא לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rav Hamnuna l'Rav
Nachman, so רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna said to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
כמאן כרבי יהודה, K'man k'Rabbi Yehuda, like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in
a ברייתא Baraisa we're about to see, that says a communal עולה,
olah, the כהנים Kohanim do not get the leather, that seems to
be how you're explaining this, but one minute, הא הדר ביה, ha
hadar beih, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda himself retracted his דרשה derasha
and said that even by a communal עולה, olah the כהנים Kohanim
get the leather. דתניא, d'tanya, where do you see this? דתניא ברייתא:
d'tanya Baraisa: ששה לנדבה לעולה הבאה מן המותרות. Shisha l'nedava l'olah habah
min hamutaros.
It talks about they had thirteen basically צדקה tzedaka boxes in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash for different funds which moneys would go to,
and of those thirteen, six of them were used
for
funds that were extra funds from a חטאת, chatas, extra funds from
an אשם asham would be put in these boxes and it would
go to these communal עולות. olos. They're doing that pretty often. Exactly.
שלא יהיו הכהנים זכאים בעורה דברי רבי יהודה. shelo yehyu hakohanim zakaim
b'orah divrei Rabbi Yehuda. Now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's almost
parenthetical to the fact that it's that, you know, that you use
these are boxes for this communal עולות. olos. Oh, by the way,
these communal עולות, olos, the כהנים Kohanim do not get its leather,
which is what we've been saying and how we've been now reading
this earlier ברייתא. Baraisa. But now the גמרא Gemara is going to
challenge this whole read because אמר לו רבי נחמיה ואמרי לה רבי
שמעון, amar lo Rabbi Nechemia v'amri lah Rabbi Shimon, so רבי נחמיה,
Rabbi Nechemia, ואמרי לה, v'amri lah, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said back,
אם כן ביטלתם מדרשו של יהוידע הכהן, im kein bitaltem midrasho shel
Yehoyada Hakohen, but then what happened to the יהוידע הכהן, Yehoyada Hakohen,
which is going back to בית ראשון Bayis Rishon times? Because if
you remember, right, the פסוק pasuk says, you know, what the פסוק
pasuk by יהוידע הכהן, Yehoyada Hakohen, it says there we read it
there on פרשת שקלים, Parshas Shekalim, right? So the פסוק pasuk is,
what's the
פסוק? pasuk? Rashi quotes it, oh, כסף אשם כסף חטאת לא יובא
בית ה' לכהנים יהיו. kesef asham kesef chatas lo yuva Beis Hashem
l'kohanim yihyu. So it says the money of a חטאת chatas and
the money of an אשם. asham. That sounds like exactly what we're
talking about. Proceeds from a חטאת chatas and an אשם, asham, it
says, לכהנים יהיו. l'kohanim yihyu. Okay? So it sounds like somehow you
repurposed this money of a חטאת chatas and an אשם asham and
nevertheless the כהנים Kohanim get it. And according to you, the כהנים
Kohanim don't get any of it. The עולה Olah. goes on the
fire and the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash gets the skin. So how
could you say that? And in these types of a communal עולות
Olos that the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash gets the skin? What happened
to יהיה לכהן? yihiyeh lakohein? He says that the כהנים Kohanim are
gonna have a portion of
it. יהוידע הכהן Yoyoda Hakohein doesn't say that. That's the... yeah, but
it's the מדרש Midrash that we're understanding is implicit in that, דתניא,
ditanya, זה מדרש דרש יהוידע הכהן, zeh Midrash darsh Yoyoda Hakohein, אשם
הוא אשם אשם להשם. asham hu ashom asham la'Hashem. Now we're going
to say his פסוק pasuk of כסף אשם וכסף חטאת kesef asham
v'kesef chatat is a דרשה derasha on this פסוק pasuk in the
תורה. Torah. That it says, this is your... it speaks about the
אשם asham of a person and then it says in it's an
אשם asham to God. So who is it? Is it the person's
or is it God's? So what we read from it is the
following: כל שבא משום חטאת ומשום אשם, kol sheba mishum chatat umishum
asham, if this אשם asham was repurposed, right, because it was leftover
or whatever, you proceed the funds were repurposed. So then normal אשם
asham we say fundamentally belongs to the כהן, Kohen, because he's going
to get all the meat and he's going to get the skin,
etc. This אשם asham is both the כהן's Kohen and an אשם
להשם. asham la'Hashem. It's an אשם להשם asham la'Hashem because it became
an עולה. Olah, Because it became an עולה, Olah. it fundamentally became
God's. What part remains the כהן's? Kohen That's the
skin. כל שבא משום חטאת ומשום אשם ילקח בו עולות. kol sheba
mishum chatat umishum asham yilakach bo olos. By עולות הבשר לשם, olos
habasar lashem, and that's אשם להשם. asham la'Hashem. It's not just an
אשם asham for the כהן Kohen because now it's an אשם asham
that became an עולה. Olah? And אורה לכהנים, orah lakohanim, that the
כהנים Kohanim get the leather. So this and we attribute this to
יהוידע הכהן Yoyoda Hakohein who says כסף חטאת וכסף אשם לא יובא
בית השם לכהנים יהיו. kesef chatat v'kesef asham lo yuva beis Hashem
lakohanim yihyu. That money ultimately the כהנים Kohanim are going to get
a portion of it. So how can you say it's a great
דרשה derasha that עולות הקדש? olos hekdesh? Because you're right, that's a
phenomenon of עולות הקדש. olos hekdesh. But presumably even רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda who said exactly that point that the כהנים Kohanim don't get
the... don't get the... that the leather was challenged and he was
silent and presumably he retracted it. So presumably we hold that the
כהנים Kohanim do get the leather there. אמר ליה, amar lei, so
he said back to him, רב נחמן Rav Nachman said back, אלא
מר במאי מוקי לה? ela mar b'mai mokim lah? If you don't
want to say that, what are you going to say is the
case of עולות הקדש olos hekdesh that the כהנים Kohanim don't get
it if you're not going to say this case of a communal
עולה? Olah אמר ליה, amar lei, מוקמינא לה במקדיש נכסיו ואליבא דרבי
יהושע. mukmina lah b'makdish nechasav v'aliba d'Rabbi Yehoshua. So now we're back
to this second interpretation we had, similar to what we said before.
Somebody sanctified all of his property. And if you sanctified all your
property and you had it in animals, what's going to be the
story with those animals? Your house, your car, those are going to
בדק הבית. bedek habayis. What's the story with your cow? And that's
going to be the example of עולות הקדש olos hekdesh that the
כהנים Kohanim don't get the skin. So it sounds similar to what
we said before, except before we had you already sanctified it as
an עולה Olah and on top of it being an עולה Olah.
you sanctified it to בדק הבית. bedek habayis. That's the... the one
we had. Now we're going to say a little bit different. You
sanctified all your stuff to בדק הבית, bedek habayis, but there was
animals in it that were fit for being an עולה. Olah. So
let's take a look. דתנן, d'tnan, we turn the משנה, Mishnah, המקדיש
נכסיו, hamakdish nechasav, you sanctified all your property, והיו בהן בהמות הראויות
לגבי מזבח זכרים ונקבות. v'hayu bahen behemot hare'uyot legabei mizbe'ach zecharim unekevot.
And you had some male and female animals and they were unblemished,
they were animals that in theory could be קרבנות. korbanot. But in
principle when you say you're sanctifying your property, it means to the
Temple Treasury. Your house, your furniture, your car, all of that is
getting sold to the Temple Treasury. How do we interpret it now
that we come to look at your nice unblemished sheep and your
nice unblemished cow? רבי אליעזר אומר זכרים ימכרו לצורכי עולות. Rabbi Eliezer
omer zecharim yimachru l'tzorchei olot. Those also belong to the Temple Treasury,
but because they are unblemished and fit for being a קרבן, korban,
so once sort of they're put in the realm of
הקדש, hekdesh, הקדש hekdesh doesn't want to lose control of them ever
to say they're not going to be a קרבן korban because that's
seen as their highest function. So it's true, this nice little unblemished
sheep is owned by the Temple Treasury. But what's the Temple Treasury
going to do with it? They're not going to just סתם stam
sell it to a farmer and have him raise it for the
wool. What they're going to do is the following: they're going to
go to you, there David, and say David, I understand that you
need to bring an עולה. Olah, We have a sheep that we
as the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash own. We will sell it to
you for $300, discount. You try to buy this off in the
marketplace, you'd pay 400. We're going to sell it to you for
300, I'm just saying that. We're going to sell it to you
for 300, you'll bring it as an עולה, Olah. but you have
to commit that you're going to bring it as an עולה. Olah,
So we're going to sell it to you for 300, you're going
to sanctify and bring it as an עולה, Olah. you anyway are
obligated an עולה. Olah That 300 you paid us is going to
go to the Temple Treasury. So in that way, both the proceeds
go to the Temple Treasury, so it was owned and they benefited
financially from owning this unblemished sheep, but the sheep in the end
is also going to be an עולה Olah. because we're selling it
to somebody who needs to bring an עולה. Olah. זכרים ימכרו לצורכי
עולה, zecharim yimachru l'tzorchei olah, sell to people who need to bring
an עולה. olah, נקבות ימכרו לצורכי זבחי שלמים. nekevot yimachru l'tzorchei zivchei
shelamim.
And the females that can't be עולות, olos, sell it to people
who need to bring a שלמים. shelamim. They'll pay us for it,
that money will go into the treasury, and they'll sanctify it and
bring a שלמים shelamim from it. ודמיהם יפלו עם שאר נכסים לבדק
הבית. v'demeihem yiplu im sh'ar nechasim l'bedek habayis. And the monies. that
they pay us for these animals, that will go with the rest
of the moneys into our bank account. Okay, so according to him,
it straight belongs to Temple Treasury, but we're going to make sure
that the animals still are used for a קרבן. korban. That's רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, Rabbi Joshua says
no, we split when you say I'm sanctifying everything, we interpret what
does it mean to sanctify based on the object you're sanctifying. So
even though you use one word, I am sanctifying, when it comes
to your furniture and your house and your car that means for
the treasury. When it came to your unblemished animals, that meant I'm
sanctifying them as a קרבן. korban. Okay. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says:
זכרים עצמן יקרבו עולות. zecharim atzman yikrevu olos.
No, the males are עולות. olos. That's how we're going to interpret
that word when it comes to your unblemished male animals. Now נקבות,
nekevos, now the females you could say do the same. Say it
means I'm sanctifying them as a שלמים. shlamim. Here's the only problem
why we're not going to say that. Because we're going to want
the word sanctify, although we're going to be very say it could
be contextual whether it means treasury or קרבן. korban. But it has
to at least have the same sense that it all goes to
the Temple. Okay, that's clearly we're going to have as a constant
meaning of that word. So if it's all going to the treasury,
it's all going to the Temple. If it's an עולה, olah, it's
all going to the Temple. But if it's a female and we
interpret it to mean a שלמים, shlamim, then I'm getting all the
meat. So it's not a close enough to the same meaning of
sanctify. So how do we interpret it in the case of a
female? So ימכרו לצורכי שלמים. yimachru l'tzorchei shlamim.
Same as before as in the earlier opinion. That means sanctified for
the Temple Treasury, we sell it to somebody who needs to bring
a שלמים, shlamim, ויביא בדמיהם עולות. v'yavi bidmeihem olos.
But here's the difference. Okay, the difference is that now when we
sell this to you David and you promise to bring it as
a שלמים, shlamim, according to the first opinion what would I have
done with that money? I would have just put it in the
Temple bank account. According to this opinion, since for the males when
I say sanctify it means that I'm bringing them as an עולה,
olah. by the females also when I say sanctify, it sort of
means I'm bringing them as an עולה. olah, What it means is
I can't bring a female as an עולה, olah. but what it
means is, I sell it to you, you bring it as a
שלמים, shlamim, the moneys that you pay get used as an עולה.
olah So it's similar in that unblemished animals the word sanctify means
for a קרבן, korban, except when it comes to the female, it
means that the proceeds are going to a
קרבן עולה, korban olah, not actually that it itself can't be an
עולה olah obviously, it's female, and it can't be a שלמים shlamim
because it has to mean a way of fully owned by the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. What does the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash get
out of this if they're going to have to use the proceeds
for...? Oh, you're right. So they don't get in this cases by
the עולה olah and by the unblemished animals, they don't get cash
in their bank account, they get more activity being done
in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Yeah. Okay, ויביא בדמיהם עולות ושאר
נכסים יפלו לבדק הבית. v'yavi bidmeihem olos ush'ar nechasim yiplu l'bedek habayis.
Now, fine. So now where do we see that the כהנים Kohanim
don't get the leather? So let's take a look. ואפילו רבי יהושע
דאמר אדם חולק הקדשו. va'afilu Rabbi Yehoshua d'amar adam cholek hekdesho. Now
it's true, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said that when it came to
the females, you basically were or the unblemished animals you were saying
that you were sanctifying them as a קרבן. korban. That's true, but
הני מילי בשר. hani mili basar. That's true that the meat was
a קרבן. korban. So now when your word I'm sanctifying it all
and the עולה olah, now, the unblemished males become an עולה, olah.
okay, that's true that the meat becomes an עולה. olah אבל עור
תפיס. aval or tafis. But the skin, that still is בדק הבית.
bedek habayis. Since when it comes to my car and my furniture
and my house when I say I'm being מקדיש makdish it means
it's Temple Treasury, so even when it comes to my unblemished male,
the word, the idea that the word מקדיש makdish means Temple Treasury
is going to extend as far possible as it can. So it's
going to extend to the skin of this unblemished sheep. That is
also going to be the Temple Treasury. Okay, only though when you
get to the actual flesh of the sheep, there then it's going
to mean it's going to be a קרבן. korban. Okay, so it's
like the idea before that you had an עולה olah and on
top of being an עולה olah you made it לבדק הבית l'bedek
habayis and therefore the skin was לבדק הבית l'bedek habayis and therefore
it's not going to be to the כהנים. Kohanim. Here though, it's
not that you first had it as an עולה olah and then
you put a הקדש hekdesh on top of it. Here from the
very outset you sanctified it, everything else was becoming בדק הבית, bedek
habayis, when you got to this sheep, the בדק הבית bedek habayis
part was relevant to the skin and the קרבן korban part was
relevant to the sheep. So in that type of a case, that's
where the כהנים Kohanim do not get the skin. Okay, so fine.
Well, okay, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi Yose b'rabbi Yehuda omer.
Fine, so that's our דרשה drasha of עולת איש olas ish? פרט
לעולת הקדש. perat l'olas hekdesh. So we have three possible interpretations. One
is when the proceeds Proceeds of a חטאת chatas and an אשם
asham get transferred into an עולה olah, and it's a communal עולה,
olah which is a very simple read of it. The only problem
is that goes against יהוידע הכהן Yehoyada HaKohen that even communal עולות
olos or whatever, the כהנים kohanim still get the skin. So therefore
we have two interpretations which are variations which are basically the animal
is an עולה olah but the skin is לבדק הבית. l'bedek habayis.
And a scenario you can do that first you make it an
עולה olah. and then בדק הבית, bedek habayis, or from the very
outset it was a type of a הקדש hekdesh that meant the
skin was לבדק הבית l'bedek habayis and the animal was an עולה.
olah. Okay. Now we get to the exclusion of עולת גרים. olas
geirim. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר Rebbe Yose Beribi Yehuda Omer פרט
לעולת גרים. p'rat l'olas geirim. אמר ליה רב סימאי בר חילקאי לרבינא:
Amar lei Rav Simai bar Chilkai l'Ravina: אטו גר לאו איש הוא?
Atu geir lav ish hu? What do you mean? Is that not
an עולת איש? olas ish, Since when is a גר geir not
a person? So אמר ליה: amar lei: פרט לגר שמת ואין לו
יורשין. p'rat l'geir shemeis v'ein lo yorshin. No, no, no. It doesn't
mean a גר. geir. It means that he died and nobody inherited
his עולה. olah. And therefore it is an ownerless עולה. olah Okay,
that's the גמרא Gemara always loves that scenario because anybody else who
dies there's some living relative, but a גר geir who dies who
doesn't leave any children that he had after converting, he has no
relatives because his birth family is not halachically recognized as his family.
And therefore the עולה olah is ownerless. So that's a nice flip,
right? Either the owner, it's not owned by a private individual, either
it's owned by the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, scenario one, or it's
ownerless, scenario two. Okay. So, now, תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: עולת איש,
olas ish, אין לי אלא עולת איש, ein li ela olas ish,
עולת גרים... olas geirim... now again they take out the word גרים
geirim because we have just said that a גר geir is obviously
included in איש. ish. So עולת נשים ועבדים מנין? olas nashim va'avadim
minayin? How do you know? איש ish might not include women. איש
ish might mean a man. איש ish might mean a free person,
not a slave. How do you know to include their עולות olos
that also this הלכה halacha applies, the כהנים kohanim get the skin?
תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: עור העולה. or ha'olah. The extra ה, hei,
it's funny, ה hei is normally a limiting word, somehow here we're
being an including word, I don't exactly get how. ריבוי, Ribuy, that's
broadening. So we don't limit it to a man, we say it
means any persons. Okay. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר עולת איש? Im
kein mah talmud lomar olas ish? So what's the limiting word of
איש? ish? Okay. עולה שעלה לאיש. Olah she'alsah l'ish. It has to
have counted. פרט שנשחטה חוץ לזמנה וחוץ למקומה. P'rat shenishchata chutz l'zimnah
v'chutz limkomah. If it's a type of a פיגול, pigul, שלא יהיו
כהנים זכאים בעורה. shelo yihyu kohanim zakaim b'orah. Therefore they don't get
it because then it never was a legitimate עולה olah. because it
was, okay, that's the דרשה drasha in the משנה. Mishnah. Now, יכול
שאני מרבה או ממעיט yachol she'ani marbeh o mamat really, שנשחטה שלא
לשמה? shenishchata shelo lishmah? If I want to take your דרשה drasha
seriously, like this proto-פיגול proto-pigul the משנה Mishnah was saying, then even
if it was שנשחטה שלא לשמה, shenishchata shelo lishmah, I would say
it might be כשר kasher but it's not עולת איש, olas ish.
it didn't count for anyone. So maybe that should be excluded as
well, as well. Top of קג עמוד ב. kuf gimmel amud beis.
לא יהיו כהנים זכאים בעורה. Lo yihyu kohanim zakaim b'orah. Maybe they
don't get the skin in that case. תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: עור
העולה. or ha'olah. Okay, מכל מקום. mikol makom. I guess the דרשה
drasha is less from the ה hei which is a limiting letter,
but from the word that the second thing it didn't say עולת
איש. olas ish It didn't say עולת איש olas ish. לכהן לו
יהיה, l'kohen lo yihyeh, it says עור העולה, or ha'olah, the עולה.
olah It doesn't have to be an עולת איש. ish, Any עולה
olah, the כהן kohen gets it. On the one hand the verse
says איש, ish. it has to be a person's עולה, olah and
the other one it says any עולה olah? the כהן kohen gets
it. It doesn't have the word איש. ish So we're going to
use that to say that it doesn't really have to be attributed
to a particular person. Even if it was שלא לשמה shelo lishmah
and no it doesn't get counted to anybody's credit, the כהנים kohanim
still get it as long as it was a valid קרבן. korban.
What we're really just excluding is an invalid קרבן. korban. Okay. Now,
so that's our משנה, Mishnah, okay, and that shows you how we're
not taking the word איש ish too seriously because it's counterbalanced by
the עור העולה or ha'olah which doesn't have that word. Now, עור
העולה, or ha'olah, אין לי אלא העולה. ein li ela ha'olah. Now
we get to the second part of the משנה. Mishnah. How do
you know to extend it beyond an עולה? olah. עורות קדשי קדשים
מנין? Oros kodshei kodashim minayin? How do you know by a חטאת
chatas and an אשם? asham? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: עור העולה אשר
הקריב. or ha'olah asher hikriv. So now we're emphasizing the words אשר
הקריב. asher hikriv. Anything you bring, any קרבן, korban, not just עולה.
olah. Okay. יכול שאני מרבה אף קדשים קלים? Yachol she'ani marbeh af
kodashim kalim? ואותו? v'oso? Maybe they get the leather by קדשים קלים,
kodashim kalim, anything that's brought goes to the כהנים? kohanim? תלמוד לומר:
עולה. talmud lomar olah. No, because we have to balance like the
same way we balance איש ish with the absence of איש and
we say it doesn't have to be a man, it doesn't even
have to be attributed to the owners, but it does have to
be כשר. kasher. Now we're balancing the word עולה olah with אשר
הקריב. asher hikriv. It doesn't have to be an עולה, olah, any
קרבן, korban, but it has to be enough like an עולה. olah.
It has to be קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. Okay. עור העולה. Or
ha'olah. Now, תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar: עולה. olah. מה עולה קדשי קדשים
אף כל קדשי קדשים. Mah olah kodshei kodashim af kol kodshei kodashim.
Okay, so it's a balance between הקריב hikriv and עולה. olah, So
it has to at least be קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. רבי ישמעאל
אומר: Rebbe Yishmael Omer: עור העולה, or ha'olah, אין לי אלא העולה.
ein li ela ha'olah. עורות קדשי קדשים מנין? Oros kodshei kodashim minayin?
He has a different דרשה, drasha, not from the אשר הקריב asher
hikriv words, but just logically if it's true by an עולה, olah,
קל וחומר kal vachomer by קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. This is how
what our משנה Mishnah says. If it's true by an עולה, olah
קל וחומר kal vachomer by קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. קדשי קדשים. kodshei
kodashim. Okay, ודין הוא, vedin hu, it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
ומה עולה שלא זכה בבשרה זכה בעורה, u'mah olah shelo zachah bivesarah
zachah beorah, by the עולה olah they didn't get the flesh and
they get the skin, so קדשי קדשים שזכה בבשרה אינו דין שזכה
בעורה? kodshei kodashim shezachah bivesarah eino din shezachah beorah? So by קדשי
קדשים kodshei kodashim I don't need אשר הקריב asher hikriv to tell
me that. I'll just say by קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim if they're
gonna get the flesh, they'll get the skin. מזבח יוכיח. mizbeach yochiach.
Now let's say you want to counter and say, wait, from the
altar we see that you can sometimes get the flesh and not
get the skin. מזבח יוכיח, mizbeach yochiach, שזכה בבשר ולא זכה בעור,
shezachah bivesar velo zachah beor, the מזבח mizbeach gets the flesh and
not the skin. No, מה למזבח שכן לא זכה במקצת. mah lemizbeach
sheken lo zachah bemiktzat. The מזבח mizbeach never gets the skin. So
the non-getting of the skin by the מזבח mizbeach is not a
counterproof. There's never a concept that you would put the skin on
the מזבח. mizbeach. תאמר בכהנים שזכו במקצת? tomar bekohanim shezachu bemiktzat? But
we know כהנים kohanim get the skin. So since we know by
an עולה olah, כהנים kohanim get the skin, I can make a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If they get the skin when they don't
get the flesh, they certainly get the skin when they do get
the flesh. הואיל וזכו במקצת זכו בכולה. ho'il vezachu bemiktzat zachu bechulah.
Okay, so that's, so one דרשה drasha that they get it by
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is אשר הקריב asher hikriv balanced by the
word עולה, olah so you know it only applies to קדשי קדשים.
kodshei kodashim. The other, it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If they
get it when they don't get the flesh, they get it when
they do get the flesh. But that קל וחומר kal vachomer assumes
the getting of the flesh, so it does not apply to the
case of a שלמים. shelamim. There they don't get the skin. רבי
אומר. Rabbi omer. Now, רבי Rabbi has a third way of saying
that they get it by קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. He says I
don't even need a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. It was patently obvious
that they got the skin by everything else. Okay, I don't need
a פסוק, pasuk, I don't even need a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
I start with an assumption that if they're getting the meat, they're
getting the skin. That's my starting point. Okay, the פסוק pasuk only
needed to tell me the הלכה halacha by an עולה olah where
the skin was different than the meat. But my whole point of
departure in anything is that the skin goes with the meat. Okay,
כל עצמו לא הוצרכנו אלא לעור העולה בלבד. kol atzmo lo hutzrachnu
ela le'or haolah bilvad. The whole פסוק pasuk was only needed by
the עולה olah. case. I don't have to figure out how do
I know קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim was obvious.
Okay, שבכל מקום העור מהלך אחר הבשר. shebechol makom ha'or mehalech achar
habasar. The skin always goes with the meat. Okay, פרים הנשרפים. parim
hanisrafim. I'll give you an example. When you burn the cows outside
the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, right, the inner חטאות, chata'ot, so ושעירים
הנשרפים הן ועורן נשרפים עמהם. u'se'irim hanisrafim hen ve'oran nisrafim imahem. You
burn it with their skin. That's explicit in the תורה. Torah. So
that part is explicit. From this point on, it's just what he's
going to assume is obvious. Okay, חטאת ואשם זבחי שלמי ציבור, chatat
ve'asham zivchei shalmei tzibur, if you have קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim that
are חטאות chata'ot or אשם asham or communal שלמים, shelamim, מתנה לכהן,
matanah lakkohen, that goes to the כהן. kohen. So since the תורה,
Torah, his point is the fact that the תורה Torah never tells
you to flay it. The only time the תורה Torah ever tells
you to flay the skin is by an עולה. olah So since
it doesn't tell you to flay it, it just says the כהנים
kohanim get it, so they get it with its skin. That's obvious.
Okay, רצו מפשיטין אותן לא רצו אוכלין אותן על גבי עורן. ratzu
mafshitin otan lo ratzu ochlin otan al gabi oran. They can decide
what to do with it. They get the whole thing, they get
the whole carcass. If they want to flay it and then eat
and then keep the skin separate and then go ahead and roast
it, go for it. You want to put it with the skin
directly on the fire and eat it off of the skin, also
be my guest. Okay, but the point is, you don't need a
פסוק pasuk to tell me or a קל וחומר kal vachomer to
tell me they get the skin. The תורה Torah never tells you
to flay it, so of course it goes together with the skin.
Okay, קדשים קלים לבעלים, kodashim kalim labe'alim, and the קדשים קלים kodashim
kalim go to the owners. רצו מפשיטין אותן, ratzu mafshitin otan, same
point. The תורה Torah never tells you flay it, so of course
the owners are going to get the skin. רצו אוכלין אותן על
גבי עורן. ratzu ochlin otan al gabi oran. So all of that,
I don't need a פסוק. pasuk. Either by the פרים הנשרפים parim
hanisrafim the תורה Torah is explicit and tells you you burn the
skin, and by everything else since it doesn't tell you to flay
it, of course the skin goes together with the flesh. Okay, so
it's not like a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Ah, if they get
the flesh, they get the skin. It's like the תורה Torah treats
it as a unit. אבל עולה נאמר בה והפשיט את העולה ונתח
אותה לנתחיה. aval olah ne'emar bah vehifshit et haolah veniteach otah linetacheha.
By the עולה olah it says flay the עולה olah. and then
cut it up into pieces. יכול לא יהו כהנים זכאים בעורה? yachol
lo yehu kohanim zakaim beorah? Since it separates the skin, who knows
what you do with the skin? Maybe you don't give it to
the כהנים. kohanim. Maybe only, right? So תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, עור
העולה אשר הקריב לכהן המקריב אותה לו יהיה. or haolah asher hikriv
lakkohen hamakriv otah lo yihyeh. Okay, so that's what you'd say. Okay,
so three different ways to get to that conclusion. One is אשר
הקריב, asher hikriv, one is a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, and the
third is what do you mean? I don't even need a פסוק.
pasuk. I started with the assumption that they were getting the skin
by everything else. I just needed the פסוק pasuk by an עולה.
olah By the way, here's something that's not being addressed. Let me
ask you a question. When by a שלמים shelamim the כהן kohen
gets the חזה chaze and the שוק, shok, who gets the skin
around the חזה chaze and the שוק shok of the שלמים? shelamim?
Right, it's not so clear. According to רבי Rabbi it's clear, if
they're going to get the actual thigh and the breast, they're going
to get the skin around it, right? But according to the other
positions, it's why is that so obvious? You know, maybe, I mean
maybe the קל וחומר kal vachomer argument you would sort of say
that it would be obvious if they're going to get anything they'll
get the flesh, קל וחומר kal vachomer they'll get the skin. But
according to the דרשה drasha of אשר הקריב, asher hikriv, right, maybe
it's not so obvious. Anyway, three different ways to get to the
idea that the כהנים kohanim get the skin. get the skin by
קדשי קדשים. kadishei kodashim. Now we're going to tie this back to
our earlier point that who gets the skin? Who's entitled when it's
the כהנים kohanim getting the skin? Who is entitled to get it?
Only the people that are entitled to get the meat, okay? It
goes with the same idea that it's הכהן המקריב, hakohen hamakriv, right
only the person who is right what's the פסוק pasuk again? We
actually quoted an excerpt. והכהן המקריב את עולת איש עור העולה אשר
הקריב לו יהיה. vehakohen hamakriv et olat ish or ha'olah asher hikriv
lo yihyeh. Right so you have to be the same way you
have to be fit to do the הקרבה hakravah in order to
get a portion of the meat, you have to be whoever's getting
a portion in the meat is getting a portion in the skin,
only if you're fit to do the הקרבה. hakravah. So that's what
we're going to focus on now. Okay, פרט לטבול יום ואונן prat
l'tuvul yom v'onen this excludes a טבול יום tuvul yom and an
אונן, onen, it's interesting why they excluded מחוסר כיפורים. mechusar kipurim. שיכול
לא יזכו בבשר sheyachol lo yizku b'vasar שהוא לאכילה shehu l'achilah maybe
the whole point before is, you know, if you can't do the
הקרבה hakravah you don't get the meat, that's because they weren't able
to eat the meat. Remember, we had a whole discussion before who's
being excluded? The people that can't do the עבודה avodah or the
people that can't do the אכילה? achilah? Right remember that was a
whole question about which way to frame it. So now we're saying,
well maybe it was basically about not being able to do the
אכילה. achilah. And therefore maybe the only thing you're excluded from is
the meat which is about eating. But maybe you were never excluded
from the skin and you get a portion in the skin. Okay,
יזכו בעור yizku b'or שאינו לאכילה she'eino l'achilah maybe you get a
portion in the skin which never was about eating. תלמוד לומר לו
יהיה. talmud lomar lo yihyeh. Really it's also the beginning of the
פסוק, pasuk, הכהן המקריב את עולת איש עור העולה לו יהיה. hakohen
hamakriv et olat ish or ha'olah lo yihyeh. Only if you're fit
to do the הקרבה hakravah do you get a portion in the
skin. The same thing as about the meat. פרט למחוסר כיפורים וטבול
יום ואונן. prat l'mechusar kipurim v'tuvul yom v'onen. Okay, so that's that
ties it up to the earlier point. Now what we're just going
to do is we're going to sort of wrap up the דרשות
drashot and we're going to say if you if one approach is
to use the word המקריב hamakriv to tell you it applies to
קדשי קדשים. kadishei kodashim. If you're not going to use the word
המקריב hamakriv for קדשי קדשים kadishei kodashim because you get it from
a קל וחומר kal vachomer because it's obvious, what are you going
to do with that extra phrase of אשר הקריב? asher hikriv? Excuse
me, of אשר הקריב. asher hikriv. Okay, ותנא קמא נמי תיפוק ליה
מדינא v'tana kama nami tipok leh midina why did the תנא קמא
tana kama need the phrase אשר הקריב asher hikriv to get קדשי
קדשים kadishei kodashim let him use רבי ישמעאל'ס Rabbi Yishmael's קל וחומר
kal vachomer if they get the meat קל וחומר kal vachomer they
get the leather. מילתא דאתי בקל וחומר טרח וכתב לה קרא. milta
d'ati b'kal vachomer tarach v'katav leh kra. No, that's not a problem.
Some things you could learn out logically and the תורה Torah still
just says it a little bit more explicitly. ורבי ישמעאל האי אשר
הקריב מאי עביד ליה? v'Rabbi Yishmael hai asher hikriv mai avid leh?
Now רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael who learns this from the קל וחומר,
kal vachomer, what does he do with the phrase אשר הקריב? asher
hikriv? He doesn't need that to teach you קדשי קדשים. kadishei kodashim.
פרט לטבול יום ומחוסר כיפורים ואונן prat l'tuvul yom umechusar kipurim v'onen
to tell you like we said a minute ago that it's you
know that it's as opposed to learning it from לו יהיה lo
yihyeh learning from אשר הקריב asher hikriv that if you're not fit
to do the עבודה avodah you don't get a portion in the
skin. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ותיפוק ליה מלו יהיה v'tipok
leh m'lo yihyeh but what about why don't learn out that from
לו יהיה lo yihyeh that if you're not fit to do the
עבודה avodah you don't get the skin? So the גמרא Gemara says
רבי ישמעאל לטעמיה. Rabbi Yishmael l'taameih. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael goes according
to his reasoning. דאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי ישמעאל d'amar Rabbi Yochanan
mishum Rabbi Yishmael נאמר בעולה לו יהיה ונאמר באשם לו יהיה. ne'emar
b'olah lo yihyeh v'ne'emar b'asham lo yihyeh. לו יהיה lo yihyeh comes
to tell you something else. Not coming to tell you that you
have to be fit to do the עבודה avodah to get the
skin, that we learn out from אשר הקריב. asher hikriv. So what's
לו יהיה lo yihyeh coming to tell you? That you get something
extra in the עולה olah that you might not have expected. And
it links it to an אשם. asham. Okay, what do you get?
Okay, מה להלן עצמותיו מותרים mah lehalan atzmotav mutarim the same way
by an אשם asham the כהן kohen gets to eat the meat
so therefore obviously he also gets to keep the bones and he
can use the bones to make you know who knows what you
know to make a bone cup or something or a bone china.
So אף כאן עצמותיו מותרים. af kan atzmotav mutarim. So the לו
יהיה lo yihyeh by an עולה olah. that links it to an
אשם asham is even though the meat goes on the מזבח, mizbeach,
the bones are like the leather. So this פסוק pasuk is and
it's a nice דרשה drasha because this פסוק pasuk is talking about
the leather so the extra לו יהיה lo yihyeh is telling you
you get something a little extra also that you get to take
home with you from an עולה. olah, Not just the עולה, olah
not just the leather, you also get the bones that you get
to take that home as well. Okay, אף כאן עצמותיו מותרים מופני.
af kan atzmotav mutarim mufni. Now the words לו יהיה lo yihyeh
is extra דאי לא מופני d'ei lo mufni if it wasn't extra
the point is that even when you make something from a גזירה
שוה gezeirah shavah linked words if the words aren't seen as being
superfluous then we won't make a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah if there's
a logical challenge to it. So here we're saying the words לו
יהיה lo yihyeh are superfluous and you can learn the הלכה halachah
from an אשם asham despite the fact that logically you could say
it's not similar to an אשם. asham. How could you say logically
it's not similar? Because if it weren't an extra word איכא למפרך
ika l'mifrach you could challenge it. מה לאשם שכן בשרו מותר. mah
l'asham sheken besaro mutar. So by an אשם asham if you get
to eat the meat you get the bones. By an עולה Ola
you don't get the meat, logically you would not assume you can
get the bones. לו יהיה קרא יתירה הוא. lo yihyeh kra yiteira
hu. So the extra לו יהיה lo yihyeh is telling you yes
it's not necessarily logically inferable but nevertheless that's the הלכה. halachah. Not
only do you get the skin, the לו יהיה lo yihyeh by
connecting to an אשם asham is saying you know what the bones
are like the skin you can also take the bones home and
make some nice bone china out of it. Okay, so that's what
we get the the idea that the skin goes with the leather,
if you're entitled to the skin, if you're, I mean the skin
goes with the meat, if you're entitled with with the meat you
get the skin and and that and that applies whether it's an
עולה or קדשי קדשים, Kodshei Kodashim, קדשים קלים Kodashim Kalim the owners
get the meat so they get so the owners get the leather
and a certain small number of cases are excepted like when the
קרבן korban is invalid or it was ownerless or it was owned
by the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or something of that nature. Now
this next משנה mishna gets back to this case of what is
the scope of that when it's invalid the כהנים kohanim do not
get the leather. And this משנה mishna seems to give a different
principle. Our משנה mishna says if it was ever valid, you know,
if it initially was valid and the כהנים kohanim were and and
the and the meat was at least initially fit for being put
on the altar, then the כהנים kohanim get the leather. Let's look
at the principle that this משנה mishna says. כל הקדשים שאירע בהם
פסול קודם להפשטן. Kol HaKodashim she-eiru bahem psul kodem le-hefshetan. The question
is when did it become invalid, okay, and not the question of
before after the blood was thrown, which was implicit in our משנה,
mishna, but before after the skin was flayed. So this is a
different way of thinking about it. Okay, does the skin go with
the meat? So if the skin was on the meat when it
became invalid, the same way the meat is invalid, the skin is
invalid or, you know, doesn't go to the כהנים. kohanim. If it
was flayed and then it became invalid, then once it was separated
physically from the skin from the skin was separated physically from the
flesh, the כהנים kohanim were entitled to the skin even if it
became invalid afterwards. So the key moment is not when the blood
was thrown, the key moment was was it kosher or פסול, pasul,
the key moment was was the skin separate from the meat when
it became kosher or פסול. pasul. Okay, so כל קדשים שאירע בהם
פסול קודם להפשטן. kol kodashim she-eiru bahem psul kodem le-hefshetan. If it
became invalid before it was flayed, אינם לכהנים. einam shel kohanim. The
כהנים kohanim do not get the skin, because then it's seen as
one package with the meat. לאחר הפשטן, Le-achar hefshatan, after it was
flayed, הרי הן לכהנים hareiy hen shel kohanim it does go to
the כהנים. kohanim. Because then it was separate. אמר רבי חנינא סגן
הכהנים Amar Rabbi Chanina Sgan Kohanim מימי לא ראיתי עור שיוצא לבית
השרפה. miyamai lo ra'isi or she-yetzei le-veis hasreifa. I never have seen
a flayed skin that went out to be burnt, you know. Now
this suggests by the way that when it becomes invalid, if the
קרבן korban is invalid, we were saying what do you do with
the skin? So I was saying well maybe the Temple takes possession
of the skin and they sell it. Now that can work in
cases like some of the exceptions we had before. An ownerless one,
a הקדש hekdesh one, there you could say the כהנים kohanim don't
get it because the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash gets it and the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash keeps it. But what do you do if
the reason the כהנים kohanim don't get it is because it was
invalid? Okay, so you could have said okay the meat's invalid, the
skin is separate, the skin you're going to go ahead and who
knows? This משנה mishna says that if at least the reason כהנים
kohanim are not getting it is because it's invalid, then in that
case it sounds like the same way you would burn the meat
you would burn the skin. Of course that's consistent with this משנה,
mishna, because this משנה mishna understands that the question is was it
flayed or not flayed. So therefore when it's not flayed it's one
unit with the flesh. So if you're burning the flesh, you're burning
the skin. Okay, so within that model that it's about flayed or
not flayed you understand that if the כהנים kohanim aren't getting it
because it's invalid and it's on still on the flesh you're going
to burn it together with the flesh, it's not going to be
that the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is going to take possession of
it. So what is רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים Rabbi Chanina Sgan Kohanim
coming and adding? He's saying I've never seen, so it sounds like
he's just reaffirming what we said before. I've never seen it separate
flayed and being burnt. So that shows you that if the problem
came after it was flayed, the כהנים kohanim still get it. That
seems to be what he's saying. But the גמרא Gemara is going
to say he's actually saying something different. He's saying it's not when
it became invalid, it's whether it actually had been flayed or not.
Because he's saying look, you could imagine a case, you flayed it,
and after you flayed it you discovered oh my god this animal
was a טרפה. treifa. Okay, so in according to the first statement
in the משנה, mishna, since the invalidity occurred before it was flayed,
it wasn't discovered till after it was flayed, but it was invalid
from you know from even before שחיטה, shechita, it was a טרפה.
treifa. In that case you would burn the skin. So according to
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma there's a scenario that you burn the
skin separate from the meat, that the כהנים kohanim don't get it.
What's the scenario? It was flayed and then it the invalidity was
discovered to have been present from earlier on. רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים
Rabbi Chanina Sgan Kohanim is saying uh-uh once it's flayed, I don't
care implicitly what he's saying is I don't care when you discovered
the invalidity. If now the skin is separate, then whenever that invalidity
was discovered, we are not going to burn the skin, we're going
to give it to the כהנים. kohanim. Okay so we have three
possibilities of when to determine the question of invalid and the כהנים
kohanim don't get the skin. Our earlier משנה mishna says was it
invalid at the time the blood was thrown, or that's implicit in
our earlier משנה. mishna. This משנה mishna says was it invalid before
or after it was flayed, and רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים Rabbi Chanina
Sgan Kohanim says as long as it was flayed you're not going
to go ahead and burn. The question of invalid and the כהנים
Kohanim don't get the skin. Our earlier משנה Mishnah says was it
invalid at the time the blood was thrown, or that's implicit in
our earlier משנה. Mishnah. This משנה Mishnah says was it invalid before
or after it was flayed, and רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים Rabbi Chanina
Sgan Hakohanim says as long as it was flayed, you're not going
to go ahead and burn it. I don't care when the invalidity
was found. Okay. אמר רבי עקיבא מדבריו למדנו שהמפשיט את הבכור ונמצא
טריפה Amar Rabbi Akiva, Midvarav Lamadnu shehamafshit et habechor venimtza treifa exactly
this: if you were to flay it and then discover that it
had been a טריפה, treifa, שיאותו הכהנים בעור, sheyoshu hakohanim ha'or, they
can get the skin. It doesn't matter that it was an earlier
invalidity. Once it was flayed, the כהנים Kohanim always get it. Okay,
so got it: again, three possibilities. Earlier משנה Mishnah is: was it
invalid when the blood was thrown? This משנה Mishnah is: was it
invalid before or after it was flayed? רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים Rabbi
Chanina Sgan Hakohanim is: I don't care when it was invalid. As
long as it was flayed, even if it was invalid earlier, the
כהנים Kohanim are going to get the skin. Okay. וחכמים אומרים Vechachamim
omrim but the חכמים Chachamim push back and they say: אין לא
ראינו ראיה, ein lo ra'inu re'aya, saying I never saw it happen
isn't a proof. Okay? Absence of proof is not proof of absence.
You might not have been around when it happened or it might
have been for thirty years in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash this
scenario never happened. That's not a proof. It is possible. Just because
you never saw a flayed skin being burnt doesn't mean that you
can't have the הלכה halacha that a flayed skin is burnt. אלא
יצא לבית השרפה. Ela yetzei l'veis hasreifa. If the invalidity was present
from earlier, even if the skin is now separate, you burn it.
Okay, so again, three possibilities. One is: it goes whether it was
invalid at the time the blood was thrown. Two is: it goes
whether it was invalid before or after it was flayed. Three is:
as long as it's flayed, the כהנים Kohanim always get it. And
again, the implication of this משנה Mishnah is that if the כהנים
Kohanim are not getting it because it's invalid, it means you're going
to burn the skin. That was not clear from the previous משנה.
Mishnah. Okay, let's just read a little bit. I know it's already
8:30, but let's just give it three more minutes, get to the
bottom of the דף. daf. כל שלא זכה מזבח בבשרו לא זכו
כהנים בעורו. Kol shelo zachah mizbe'ach mibsaro, lo zachu kohanim b'oro. So
now we're going to just point out the difference between our משנה
Mishnah and this משנה. Mishnah. Our earlier משנה Mishnah said that it
goes with whether the meat was fit to be on the altar.
Okay, so that sounds like it's irrelevant whether it was flayed, אף
על גב דאפשטיה לעור קודם זריקה. af al gav d'afshateih l'or kodem
zerika. It sounds like you could have imagined that you flayed it
before you got around to throwing the blood. Then you threw the
blood with a פיגול piggul thought. Okay, so according to our משנה,
Mishnah, the כהנים Kohanim would not get the leather because it was
invalid at the time of the blood being thrown. But according to
this משנה, Mishnah, the כהנים Kohanim would get the leather. Okay, so
מני, mani, רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון היא, Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon hi,
דאמרי, d'amri, אין הדם מרצה אלא לעור בפני עצמו, ein hadam mirtzeh
ela l'or bifnei atzmo, that the blood, you know, when the blood
is being thrown, it doesn't matter that the skin is set... that
the skin has been flayed and is separate. If when the blood
is being thrown the meat is invalid, okay, like it was פיגול,
piggul, then even if the skin had been separated already, nevertheless, the
whole thing is invalid. The כהנים Kohanim don't get it. Okay, which
is again a way of saying like from our earlier משנה Mishnah
the key was when the blood was thrown. And even if it
had been flayed at that time, it doesn't matter. If it's invalid
when the blood is thrown, the כהנים Kohanim don't get it. That's
point number one. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, let's look at our משנה.
Mishnah. כל הקודם להפשטן פסול הן אינם שלהם לכהנים. Kol hakodem l'hefshatan
pesul hen, einam shelahem lakohanim. לאחר הפשטן אותם לכהנים. L'acher hefshatan, otam
lakohanim. It all goes by when it was flayed. So if you
flayed it first and then made it פיגול, piggul, the כהנים Kohanim
would get the skin, okay, since it was separate at the time
it became פסול. pasul. אתו לרבי, Atu l'Rebbi, that's going to go
like רבי. Rebbi. We're going to see these positions tomorrow's דף. daf.
דאמר, d'amar, הדם מרצה לעור בפני עצמו, hadam mirtzeh l'or bifnei atzmo,
that if you have the skin separate from the meat and you
throw the blood, then you treat that the skin separate from the
meat. The throwing of the blood doesn't package it all together with
the meat. Okay, so this question: does the blood act on the
skin separate from the meat or not is another way of framing
it. But let's just focus concretely: the earlier משנה Mishnah said it
goes by when the blood is thrown, and even if it's flayed,
if when the blood is thrown it's invalid, the כהנים Kohanim don't
get it. And our משנה Mishnah says it goes by when it's
been flayed. And if by the time the blood is and if
the blood is thrown invalidly but it's already separate, the כהנים Kohanim
do get it. So what's the story? Does it go by when
it's flayed or does it go by when the blood is thrown?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: רישא רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון
סיפא רבי? reisha Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon, seifa Rebbi? How can you
have these two back-to-back משניות mishnayot that are giving different criteria? So
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, מדיסיפא רבי היא רישא נמי רבי היא. mideseifa
Rebbi hi reisha nami Rebbi hi. I'm going to interpret it all
following רבי, Rebbi, that it really goes by when it was flayed.
So then why does our משנה Mishnah say it goes by when
the blood was thrown? Because ומודה רבי שאין הפשט קודם זריקה. u'modeh
Rebbi she'ein hefshat kodem zerika. Practically speaking, like the end of the
משנה, Mishnah, you know, practice and theory don't always line up. In
theory you're right. Could I have the blood being thrown and the
כהנים Kohanim get the skin if it was already flayed? Yes. But
in practice you never would flay it before the blood was thrown,
right? Takes a long time to flay something, takes two seconds to
throw it, and it's not appropriate to have caught the blood and
waiting an hour to get the thing flayed before throwing it. So
in practice it'll never be flayed before the blood is thrown. And
that's why the משנה Mishnah says you look at the time the
blood was thrown. But in theory you're right. The real critical question
is, was it flayed before did the invalidity happen after it had
been flayed or before it had been flayed? If the invalidity happened
after it had been flayed, if in theory you waited to throw
the blood till after it had been flayed and then it became
invalid when you threw the blood, you're right, the כהנים Kohanim would
get the leather. So we really do go by when it was
flayed, except that that scenario is a very unlikely one but that
is the הלכה. halacha. We go by when it was flayed. That's
that position. רב אמר מדרישא רבי אליעזר בן שמעון סיפא נמי רבי
אליעזר בן שמעון. Rav amar mide-reisha Rabbi Eliezer ben Shimon seifa nami
Rabbi Eliezer ben Shimon. No, the opposite, that it really goes not
by when it was flayed, it really goes by when the blood
was thrown. ומאי קודם הפשט ומאי אחר הפשט, U'mai kodem hefshet u'mai
achar hefshet, so what does it mean in our משנה, Mishnah, has
it been flayed or has it not been flayed? It doesn't mean
literally had it been flayed. What it means is קודם שנראו להפשט
ואחר שנראו להפשט. kodem sheniru le-hafshet ve-achar sheniru le-hafshet. When our משנה
Mishnah says did the invalidity happen before or after it had been
flayed, it doesn't mean that. It means did the invalidity happen before
or after the blood was thrown. The point is that after the
blood was thrown is the time when it's fit to be flayed.
Okay. So it's just another complicated way of
saying you go by the time when the blood was thrown, but
the conceptual reason is because that was when it was ready to
be flayed. So we have here again two positions bracketing רבי חנינא
סגן הכהנים, Rabbi Chanina Segan ha-Kohanim, okay? It goes by whether it
was invalid at the time the blood was thrown or it goes
by whether it was invalid after or before it had been flayed.
In order to make the משנה Mishnah all say one or the
other but not be contradictory, we could either say it all goes
by when it's been flayed and in practice though it'll never be
flayed before the blood was thrown so in practice you're really not
going to have so much of a gap in practice, okay, because
you're never really going to get the scenario of it being flayed
before the blood was thrown. Or it all goes by when the
blood is thrown and the משנה Mishnah that says about has it
been flayed or not doesn't literally mean that, it really means has
it gotten to the time when it's ready to be flayed. Okay,
did it happen before or after the blood was put on the
altar. Okay, so we will continue with this question about what is
the critical time for determining whether the כהנים Kohanim get the skin,
the time of flaying or the time of the throwing of the
blood. We'll continue with this tomorrow.